Guide to the Animal prints theft collection, 1859-2004 MS 544
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Animal prints theft collection
1859-2004
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Rice University
MS 544
1.5 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
This collection consists of circa 700 color prints stolen from the journals (the journal of the British Ornithologists' Union) and Proceedings of the Zoological Society of London, owned by the Fondren Library. The prints date from 1859-1915 and feature birds, bird eggs, and other animals. Theft correspondence and research dates from 1980-2004 and represents the Fondren Library's efforts to cooperate with and assist in the Blumberg investigation.
Biographical Note
Stephen Carrie Blumberg was an accomplished book thief who stole 18,900 books from 327 libraries and museums in 45 states and Canada before being caught in 1991. Over 20 years he amassed his collection of rare books in his Iowa home in an attempt to create his own rare book collection, never intending to sell them. Blumberg stole numerous color plates from journals in Rice's Fondren Library in the 1980s. When the FBI confiscated his collection, and attempted to return the books to the libraries from which they were stolen, the task was complicated by the fact that Blumberg had removed each library's ownership marks. It is believed that this group of prints represents only what was stolen from Fondren Library, but complete accuracy on this point is not possible. It was also determined that the original journals from which these plates were cut were in such bad condition that returning the plates to them would not be possible. Therefore they have been maintained in their original order since their investigation and return.
Blumberg's stolen book collection was valued at $5.3 million. He served nearly 6 years in prison for the thefts.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of circa 700 color prints stolen from the journals Ibis (the journal of the British Ornithologists' Union) and Proceedings of the Zoological Society of London, owned by the Fondren Library. The prints date from 1859-1915 and feature birds, bird eggs, bird nests and other animals. The prints were recovered after Blumberg's 1991 arrest and returned to Fondren Library. The bags in which they are stored are the bags which Blumberg used for them. The folder names for the bags reflect his labeling on the bags. Theft correspondence and research dates from 1980-2004 and represents the Fondren Library's efforts to cooperate with and assist in the Blumberg investigation. Additionally, Series III includes plates recovered from other unidentified sources, probably unrelated to the thefts from Ibis and the Journal of Zoology. These prints were found in the collections at the Woodson Researcher Center with no provenance information, but are similar in nature to the other plates in this collection, and so are being included here.
Access Restriction
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center and requires 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Acquisition Information
The theft correspondence and research in this collection was the work product of the Fondren Library in collaboration with the FBI and other libraries which were involved, over the period of time 1981-2004.
Index Terms
Subjects
Book thefts; Environment
Document Types
plates (illustrations); corrrespondence
Places
Art
Subjects (Persons)
Blumberg, Stephen Carrie
Subjects (Corporations)
Rice University
- Series I: Theft correspondence and research, 1980-2004, 47180
  - Composite of information on stolen plates, 47189 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Two page sheet detailing the bibliographic description of the journal Ibis and police reports detailing contents of plastic bags containing stolen plates.
  - Hartfield catalogue of rare books, 47188 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Catalogue from Hartfield's Fine and Rare Books store dated February 11, 1985. Contains information of the value of some of the stolen plates (listing # L-74).
  - Printouts of Fondren Library's journal holdings, 47187 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Printout details the location and volumes of journals held by Fondren from which plates were stolen.
  - Bibliographic listings and police report, 47186 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Photocopies of illustration listings contained in Alfred Guernsey's book "Harper's Pictorial History of the Civil War" dated 1868.
  - Listings of illustrations in volumes, 47185 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Bibliographic listings of Fondren's holdings that are missing (with sample plates), dated May 12, 1981.
  - Collection of catalog listings, 47184 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    A collection of handwritten and typed notes containing bibliographic listings of journals and books originally thought to hold the stolen plates. Annotations by librarians concerning the status of the plates are also present.
  - Photocopies of Ibis plate listings, 47183 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    A collection photocopies from Ibis's plate listings in the order in which they appear in their original publications.
  - Titles not reviewed or reported to F.B.I. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - The Shinn Lists (1982), 47182 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    One hundred forty-four page booklet edited by William Moffett of Oberlin College listing the books stolen by another book thief, James Shinn. This booklet was created to facilitate communication between universities that had been victims of Shinn when the recovered books ended up at the wrong libraries.
  - "Stephen Blumberg and His Stolen Books", 47181 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Printout from the Web of the November 1991 edition of the Abbey Newsletter detailing Stephen Blumberg's life and history of his thefts.
- Series II: Prints, 1859-1915, 47190
  - Sub-series A: Journal of Zoology; Proceedings of the Zoological Society of London
    - 1864 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 1865 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1866 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 1868 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 1869 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - 1870 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - 1871 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - 1872 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - 1874 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - 1875 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - 1876 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - 1879 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - 1880 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - 1881 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - 1882 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - 1883 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - 1884 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - 1885 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - 1887 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - 1889 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - 1896 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - 1897 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - 1899 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - 1900 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - no date (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Sub-series B: Ibis (British Ornithologists' Union
    - 1859 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 1860 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - 1861 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - 1862 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - 1863 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - 1864 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - 1865 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - 1867 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - 1869 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - 1870 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - 1874 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - 1876 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - 1877 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - 1882 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - 1884 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - 1885 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - 1886 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - 1887 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - 1888 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - 1889 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - 1890 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - 1891 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - 1892 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - 1894 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - 1896 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - 1897 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - 1898 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - 1899 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - 1900 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - 1901 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - 1902 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - 1903 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - 1904 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - 1905 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - 1906 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - 1907 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - 1908 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - 1909 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - 1910 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - 1911 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - 1912 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - 1913 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - 1914 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - no date (Box 2, Folder 44)
- Series III: Mixed plates recovered from other sources
  - Flora and Fauna (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Broadway Hotel - Cincinnati, U.S.A (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - American Civil War - Confederacy Generals (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - American Civil War - Union General U.S. Grant (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - American Patriots Patrick Henry & Benjamin Franklin (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - European Nobility & Persons of Interest (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - View of Paris from Village of Chaillot, 1753 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - German Notice, 1782-04-13 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Imperial Palace of Petrovski, near Moscow (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Mustafa III Grand Seignor (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - A Persian Lady, a Persian smoking on horseback with servant & hookah (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - General View of the Pyramids of Giza [with Sphinx] (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Views of Homes, Castles, & Palaces (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Portrait Gallery of Historic Person: Queen Elizabeth, Saints, Paracelsus (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Historical Views of Balls & Court Presentation, Court of St. James (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Views of Cities - England (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Views of Public Buildings (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - English Judges - Esq. - RT. Hon. (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Bouverie - Earl of Radnor (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Pedigree of the Ancient & Honorable Family of Curzon (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Princes, Earls & Dukes (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Military - R.N. - R.B. (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Satire - Political & Social (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Theatre and Drama II (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Theatre & Drama I (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - 3 Allegorical Frontispieces (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - New Lady's Magazine - A French Lady, 1786-1787 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - English Men & Women (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - 10 Oval Portraits (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Rural Life (Box 3, Folder 30)